Wilbur C. Hallenbeck Papers
Wilbur C. Hallenbeck Papers
1887-1987
1971-1975
Hallenbeck, Wilbur C., 1892-1986
1 linear ft.
Papers consist primarily of correspondence, planning materials and proposals related to the "University Without Walls" program at Roger Williams College in Rhode Island. There are also some reports, pamphlets, books and dissertations.
149423
Biographical History
Wilbur Hallenbeck began his career as a Presbyterian minister, having graduated San Francisco Theological Seminary. In 1932, he received his doctorate from Columbia University Teacher's College in adult education, and joined the faculty as professor of adult education and sociology. Hallenbeck's work included consulting with the United States military in Korea and at the University of Natal in Durban, South Africa. After his retirement in 1958, Hallenbeck held visiting professorships at the University of British Columbia in Vancouver, at the University of Michigan and at the University of Wisconsin.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The collection consists primarily of the proposals, correspondence, and planning materials related to the "University Without Walls" program at Roger Williams College in Rhode Island, where Hallenbeck's son was project director. In addition there are some miscellaneous pamphlets and reports, two books with dedications, and two typescript dissertations. The bulk of the material is dated 1971-1975.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection begins with the "University Without Walls" materials, and is followed by the miscellaneous pamphlets and reports and the dissertations. Each of these three small divisions is arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing.
In particular, see the Joseph W. Jacques Tape Recordings for a tape-recorded interview with Hallenbeck
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Hallenbeck, Wilbur C. (Wilbur Chapman), b. 1892, Archives; Verner, Coolie; Roger Williams College; University Without Walls; Adult education; Educators, United States; Correspondence.; Pamphlets.; Reports.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- University Without Walls
  - Alternate Learning Project (High School) (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1981 (Box 1)
  - "Education is Experience" - WCH, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Evaluation workshop (Box 1)
  - First report, 1971? (Box 1)
  - Handbook, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Information and forms, 1974 (Box 1)
  - "Non-Collegiate Sector: Statistical Snapshots of Adult Continuing Education" - Address, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Notes, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Preliminary planning paper, 1973 (Box 1)
  - "On Choosing a Facilitator" (proposal) - WCH (Box 1)
  - Union Graduate School proposal, 1974 (Box 1)
- Books
  - Adult Education (C. Verner and A. Booth), 1964; dedication copy (Box 1)
  - Education for Literacy (R. Narain), 1958; dedication copy (Box 1)
  - Education in Urban Society (B.J. Chandler, Lindley J. Stiles, and John I. Kitsuse), 1962 (Box 1)
- Pamphlets and reports
  - Grace Hewell (U.S. Govt.) (Box 2)
  - "History of the Nottingham Mechanic's Institution", 1887 (Box 2)
  - Invitation, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Obituaries, correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets (Box 2)
  - "Reflections of an Adult Educator" - WCH, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Reports, 1963 (Box 2)
- Dissertations
  - Dissertation, Joe William Underwood, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Dissertation, Karen Ann Waldron, 1975; 2 folders (Box 1)